{"tossups":[{"question":"A word ending with this suffix is contrasted with “acting basic” and “mass indie” in Youth Mode: A Report on Freedom, a 2014 text by the artist collective K-HOLE which popularized that word. A word ending with this suffix was coined in 2000 by MC Frontalot, who wrote the theme song for the webcomic Penny Arcade. Andrew Bujalski’s (*) Funny Ha Ha is sometimes said to be the first work to exemplify another word that ends with this suffix. Taylor Swift’s album Folklore is often described using a word with this suffix, referring to an aesthetic that idealizes rural life. For 10 points, what suffix appears in the names of many subcultures and musical genres and can follow words like “nerd,” “mumble,” “cottage,” and “norm”?","formatted_answer":"-<b><u>core<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>normcore<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>nerdcore<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>mumblecore<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>cottagecore<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"-<b><u>core<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>normcore<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>nerdcore<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>mumblecore<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>cottagecore<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":1},{"question":"A bundle of isoglosses named for two cities in this country demarcates features like the pronunciation of the letter “c,” the formation of plural nouns, and the preservation of geminate consonants. An informal greeting that originated in this country derives from a phrase meaning “I am your slave.” A word from this country refers to retired men who spend their time observing (*) construction sites and offering unsolicited advice. Argentina’s lunfardo [loon-FAR-doh] argot is named after a region of this European country. A phrase meaning “What do you want?” in this country’s official language refers to a hand gesture which is represented by the “pinched fingers” emoji. For 10 points, name this country home to linguistic varieties like Piedmontese and Sardinian.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Italy<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Italia<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>Italian<\/b><\/u> Republic; or Repubblica <b><u>Italiana<\/b><\/u>] (The first three clues refer to the La Spezia-Rimini line, the word ciao, and the word umarell.)","answer":"<b><u>Italy<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Italia<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>Italian<\/b><\/u> Republic; or Repubblica <b><u>Italiana<\/b><\/u>] (The first three clues refer to the La Spezia-Rimini line, the word ciao, and the word umarell.)","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":2},{"question":"A paper on the “causes and consequences” of some of these words was co-written by Roland G. Fryer, Jr. based on a large database on the usage of these words in California. A psychological effect related to these words was discovered in the 1980s by Jozef Nuttin, who framed it in terms of the mere ownership effect. The fact that people tend to prefer letters that (*) appear in these words over other letters of the alphabet has been leveraged in tests for estimating implicit self-esteem. Dozens of studies have analyzed racial discrimination in hiring by sending out fake résumés with these words altered. For 10 points, name these words which affect people’s life choices, according to the theory of nominative determinism.","formatted_answer":"personal <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s [accept first <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s; accept given <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s; accept last <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s; accept <b><u>surname<\/b><\/u>s; accept family <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s]","answer":"personal <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s [accept first <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s; accept given <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s; accept last <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s; accept <b><u>surname<\/b><\/u>s; accept family <b><u>name<\/b><\/u>s]","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":3},{"question":"A poem that was once thought to contain the first appearance of this word says that this thing “is not a leukoma of dead liquid over the earth’s dead eye” and is “neither tower nor cathedral.” This word was first used in a literary journal co-founded by the author of the poetry collection Pigments. This word is called a “rather ugly term” in an essay that calls this concept a form of (*) “anti-racist racism,” written by Jean-Paul Sartre [sart]. Wole Soyinka [wah-lay shoh-yeen-kah] supposedly combined this word with the word “tiger” to criticize this term, which was coined by the Martinican author of Notebook of a Return to My Native Land. For 10 points, what word approximately meaning “blackness” is the name of a literary movement that included Aimé Césaire [em-ay say-ZAIR] and Léopold Senghor [lay-oh-pald sahn-GOR]?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Négritude<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>Négritude<\/b><\/u>","category":"Literature","subcategory":"European Literature","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":4},{"question":"In the 1880s, a series of these events in D.C. was put on by William Dorsey Swann, a man who was born into slavery and who coined a common term for participants in these events. These events are the origin of the word “banjee,” which inspired the stage name of José Cancel [con-SELL]. The slang term “dip,” which originated at these events, has been superseded in the popular consciousness by the terms “shablam” and (*) “death drop.” Dorian Corey defines a word by saying “I don’t tell you you’re ugly, but I don’t have to tell you, because you know you’re ugly” in Jennie Livingston’s documentary about these events, Paris Is Burning. For 10 points, slang terms like “voguing” and “throwing shade” were introduced at what events that often feature cross-dressing performers?","formatted_answer":"drag <b><u>ball<\/b><\/u>s [accept <b><u>drag<\/b><\/u> shows] (William Dorsey Swann was the first person to describe himself as a drag queen.)","answer":"drag <b><u>ball<\/b><\/u>s [accept <b><u>drag<\/b><\/u> shows] (William Dorsey Swann was the first person to describe himself as a drag queen.)","category":"Literature","subcategory":"American Literature","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":5},{"question":"References to this author on Gilmore Girls presumably introduced many viewers to the word “chrestomathy” [cress-TAH-muh-thee], meaning a collection of literary passages. This author used a German compound meaning “dictionary of vituperation,” Schimpflexikon [SHIMF-lex-uh-con], for the title of a collection of quotations denouncing this author. In the preface to a pioneering 1919 book, this writer complained about the “absurd efforts to prove that no such thing as an (*) American variety of English existed.” This coiner of the word “booboisie” [boob-wah-ZEE] used a creative spelling to render an American pronunciation of the phrase “beaux arts” [boh-ZAR] in the title of his essay “The Sahara of the Bozart.” The book The American Language is by, for 10 points, what journalist and satirist from Baltimore?","formatted_answer":"H. L. <b><u>Mencken<\/b><\/u> [or Henry Louis <b><u>Mencken<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"H. L. <b><u>Mencken<\/b><\/u> [or Henry Louis <b><u>Mencken<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":6},{"question":"A phrase ending with a form of this word was popularized by Rosa Luxemburg, who attributed it to Friedrich Engels even though it was probably introduced by Karl Kautsky. A form of this word is used analogously to the word “solecism” [SAHL-us-ism] to refer to an error in word usage as opposed to an error in syntax. A word that is probably derived from the Greek word rha [rah] plus the Greek root of this word is traditionally used by stage actors to imitate the sound of (*) indistinct conversation. This word, which may come from an imitation of the gibberish-like sound of foreign languages, originally referred to any non-Greek speaker. For 10 points, what word referring to uncivilized or warlike people describes Conan in the title of an Arnold Schwarzenegger film?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>barbarian<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>barbarism<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>barbarous<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>barbarity<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>bárbaros<\/b><\/u>; accept Socialism or <b><u>Barbarism<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>barbarian<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>barbarism<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>barbarous<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>barbarity<\/b><\/u>; or <b><u>bárbaros<\/b><\/u>; accept Socialism or <b><u>Barbarism<\/b><\/u>]","category":"History","subcategory":"European History","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":7},{"question":"A typeface designed especially for use on these objects is called FE-Schrift [F-E-shrift]. George Maynard covered up some words on one of these objects on the grounds that they were repugnant to his beliefs as a Jehovah’s Witness, leading to the Supreme Court case Wooley v. Maynard. An episode of 99% Invisible describes a rash of thefts of these objects in (*) Idaho that followed the revolutionary addition of words to them in 1928. On the Seinfeld episode “The Fusilli Jerry,” a mixup with a proctologist causes Kramer to receive some of these objects with the words “ass man” on them. In D.C., most of these objects display the phrase “taxation without representation.” For 10 points, words can be spelled out on customized “vanity” versions of what objects used by motorists?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>license plate<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>vehicle registration plate<\/b><\/u>s; or <b><u>number plate<\/b><\/u>s; prompt on <u>plate<\/u>s]","answer":"<b><u>license plate<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>vehicle registration plate<\/b><\/u>s; or <b><u>number plate<\/b><\/u>s; prompt on plates]","category":"Other Academic","subcategory":"Other Academic","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":8},{"question":"Aleister Crowley added a silent “g” and an “n” to this word to form a compound letter whose numerical values add up to 93, just like the words “thelema” [thuh-LEE-muh] and “agape” [ah-GAH-pay]. This word is symbolically spoken by pairs of lion-like statues, one of which has an open mouth and one of which has a closed mouth. Symbols for guttural and labial sounds are combined with a diacritic consisting of a (*) dot inside the bottom half of a circle to form a ligature representing this word in Devanagari [day-vuh-NAH-guh-ree]. A six-syllable phrase starting with this word is described as the “innermost heart” of Avalokiteśvara [UH-vuh-loh-kih-TAYSH-vuh-ruh]. For 10 points, name this sacred sound in Hinduism and Buddhism which, in a Sanskrit mantra, is followed by “mani padme hum” [mah-nih pod-may hoom].","formatted_answer":"<b><u>om<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>aum<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>om<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>aum<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Religion","subcategory":"Religion","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":9},{"question":"This person imagined a mathematician who discovers an integer between 6 and 7 and invents the word “bleen” to describe it. In describing “double-meaning words,” this person said “You can prick your finger, but don’t finger your prick.” This author of the posthumous autobiography Last Words also described words that will “infect your soul, curve your spine, and keep the (*) country from winning the war.” The court case FCC v. Pacific Corporation was sparked by a broadcast in which this person mused that “tits” is a “friendly sounding word” that doesn’t belong on a list with other taboo words like “piss” and “motherfucker.” For 10 points, what comedian performed the “seven words you can never say on television” monologue?","formatted_answer":"George (Denis Patrick) <b><u>Carlin<\/b><\/u>","answer":"George (Denis Patrick) <b><u>Carlin<\/b><\/u>","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":10},{"question":"Whimsical words for this thing, including “creaky-creaky” and “spangladasha,” are recited by a professor named Joe, who is played by Stephen Fry, in a 2011 song. Laura Martin’s research on words for this thing is cited in an essay that quotes a Hartford fire prevention engineer’s quote about “sensuously and operationally different” forms of this thing. Words for this thing are the subject of that Geoff Pullum essay titled for a (*) “vocabulary hoax.” Adaptable clichés such as “have X, will travel” are referred to as “clones” named after this thing. English words for classifying this thing include “firn,” “névé” [NAY-vay], and “powder.” For 10 points, a largely discredited argument for linguistic relativity states that the Yupik and Inuit languages have numerous words for what form of precipitation?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>snow<\/b><\/u> [accept 50 Words for <b><u>Snow<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>snowclone<\/b><\/u>s]","answer":"<b><u>snow<\/b><\/u> [accept 50 Words for <b><u>Snow<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>snowclone<\/b><\/u>s]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Other Science","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":11},{"question":"This color is also the last name of a text artist whose word-painting Nixon is the cover for Lambchop’s album Nixon. Definitions of words are presented in text of this color in Joseph Kosuth’s Art as Idea as Idea series. A work featuring text of this color was rediscovered at Barter Books in 2000, having been largely forgotten even though millions of copies were printed after its 1939 creation. The font Futura Bold is often used for text in this color by an (*) artist who inspired the logo for the apparel brand Supreme. That artist used this color to write phrases like “I shop therefore I am” and “your body is a battleground.” For 10 points, words are written in what color against a red background in many works of Barbara Kruger and on the propaganda poster “Keep Calm and Carry On”?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>white<\/b><\/u> [accept Wayne <b><u>White<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>white<\/b><\/u> [accept Wayne <b><u>White<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":12},{"question":"Computer-generated anagrams of this politician’s personal motto appear as subtitles in Joyce Wieland’s film Reason over Passion. The phrase “low bridge” was used to describe this politician’s strategy of ducking the press during an election in which this politician defeated a Progressive Conservative leader who had governed for less than a year. After being accused of mouthing the words “fuck off” in the (*) House of Commons, this politician infamously used the words “fuddle duddle.” This politician first used the phrase “just society” to describe his vision for his country in 1968, during the period of excitement known as his “mania.” For 10 points, name this Prime Minister of Canada for most of the period from 1968 to 1984, whose son is the current Prime Minister.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>P<\/b><\/u>ierre Elliott <b><u>Trudeau<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Joseph<\/b><\/u> Philippe Pierre Yves Elliott <b><u>Trudeau<\/b><\/u>; prompt on <u>Trudeau<\/u>; do not accept or prompt on “J. Trudeau” or “Justin Trudeau”; accept <b><u>Trudeaumania<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>P<\/b><\/u>ierre Elliott <b><u>Trudeau<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>Joseph<\/b><\/u> Philippe Pierre Yves Elliott <b><u>Trudeau<\/b><\/u>; prompt on Trudeau; do not accept or prompt on “J. Trudeau” or “Justin Trudeau”; accept <b><u>Trudeaumania<\/b><\/u>]","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":13},{"question":"This food provides the nickname of the paper “Contrastive Focus Reduplication in English.” A variety of this food is named after the highly secretive chef of Moscow’s Hermitage restaurant, Lucien Olivier. Another variety of this food is named for the owner of Hollywood’s Brown Derby restaurant. The name of a popular meze [MEH-zay] combines the Greek word for this food with the Greek word for cod roe, (*) taramás [tah-rah-MOSS]. An idiom mentioning this food derives from a passage in Antony and Cleopatra describing a time when Cleopatra was “cold in blood.” Speech consisting of an unintelligible mixture of words is nicknamed for this food. For 10 points, anilingus [AY-nuh-LING-gus] is slangily described as “tossing” what kind of food?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>salad<\/b><\/u> [accept the <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>-salad paper; accept Olivier <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>; accept Cobb <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u> days; accept word <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>; accept tossing <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>]  Note to players: You should give the common English translation of the words in question.","answer":"<b><u>salad<\/b><\/u> [accept the <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>-salad paper; accept Olivier <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>; accept Cobb <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u> days; accept word <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>; accept tossing <b><u>salad<\/b><\/u>]  Note to players: You should give the common English translation of the words in question.","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":14},{"question":"Extensive borrowing of this word across northeast Asia is suggested by similar forms like the Manchu morin [moh-reen], the Mongolian mori [murr], and comparable Japanese and Korean words. The Proto-Celtic *markos [MAR-kohss] and Proto-Germanic *marhaz [MAR-hozz] are translations of this word which may derive from a common Proto-Indo-European root. An adjective meaning (*) “swift” is the likely source of a PIE [P-I-E] root for this word, which, in the original version of Schleicher’s fable, is reconstructed as akvāsas [ahk-VAH-“sauce”]. This word is common to the etymologies of the names of the Ashvin twins and the goddess Epona. The name “Philip” derives from the Greek Philippos, meaning a lover of these animals. For 10 points, name this animal which is called equus [“ACHE”-wooss] in Latin.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>horse<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>horse<\/b><\/u>","category":"History","subcategory":"Other History","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":15},{"question":"As part of a viral marketing project that also involved the Twitter account “Horse_ebooks,” a provider of these things started cryptically counting down to the date “September 24, 2013.” A seminal 1917 book of these things by Daniel Jones included the first appearance of Jones’s diagram of eight “cardinal” reference points. Words appear in black on a grayish background on a parody YouTube channel that purports to be a (*) “manual” of these things. User-provided examples of these things are hosted by the website Forvo. Though they don’t usually use the IPA, American dictionaries tend to follow the “one-symbol-per-sound” principle when providing these things. For 10 points, name these things that are added to Quizbowl questions to help moderators deal with difficult words.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>pronunciation<\/b><\/u> guides [or <b><u>PG<\/b><\/u>s]","answer":"<b><u>pronunciation<\/b><\/u> guides [or <b><u>PG<\/b><\/u>s]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":16},{"question":"The personal motto of a ruler from this royal house was ironically referenced in the name of the defensive lines that were breached during the Siege of Bouchain. Another ruler from this house used a motto which is Latin for “let justice be done, though the world perish.” A phrase meaning “all the world is subject to [a certain country]” may be the origin of this house’s enigmatic motto (*) “A.E.I.O.U.” A 16th-century ruler from this house used the motto “plus ultra.” The bureaucracy of this house was mocked using the name “Kakania,” which is a reference to the abbreviation “k. u. k.” That abbreviation, which means “imperial and royal,” refers specifically to a dual monarchy ruled by this house from 1867 to 1918. For 10 points, name this royal house that ruled Austria-Hungary.","formatted_answer":"House of <b><u>Habsburg<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Habsburg<\/b><\/u>-Lorraine]","answer":"House of <b><u>Habsburg<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Habsburg<\/b><\/u>-Lorraine]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"European Literature","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":17},{"question":"This proper noun is part of the nickname given by William Safire to a 1991 speech in which George H. W. Bush warned against “suicidal nationalism.” During a public hearing in 2019, many viewers were surprised to hear the diplomats George P. Kent and William B. Taylor Jr. pronounce this word with a single syllable. In the original script, the two controversial letters in this word resemble a backwards capital (*) N and an I topped with a diaeresis [“dye-AIR-uh-sis”]. Two spellings of this word are used in a hashtag promoted as part of the “CorrectUA” campaign, which prompted many western media outlets and the U.S. Board on Geographic Names to adopt the preferred spelling in 2019. For 10 points, efforts to undo Russification have promoted the native spelling of what city, the capital of Ukraine?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Kyiv<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Kiev<\/b><\/u>; accept Chicken <b><u>Kiev<\/b><\/u> speech]","answer":"<b><u>Kyiv<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Kiev<\/b><\/u>; accept Chicken <b><u>Kiev<\/b><\/u> speech]","category":"History","subcategory":"European History","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":18},{"question":"The word for one of these things comes from a Syriac word for “orpiment” which was adopted into Greek via a folk etymology linking it to a word meaning “virile.” One of these things was given a name referencing Cassiopeia [kass-ee-uh-PEE-uh] by Carl Auer von Welsbach [VELLS-bok], and that name was commonly used in Germany for nationalistic reasons until the 1950s. From the 1960s to the 1990s, institutions called LBNL and JINR were involved in a series of  (*)“wars” over the names for some of these things. A scientist best known for studying these things named some of them using a prefix meaning “one” in Sanskrit, eka. In 2016, four of these things, including oganesson [oh-guh-NESS-on], were given their official names by IUPAC [EYE-yoo-pak]. For 10 points, identify these things whose names often end with the suffix “-ium.”","formatted_answer":"chemical <b><u>element<\/b><\/u>s","answer":"chemical <b><u>element<\/b><\/u>s","category":"Science","subcategory":"Chemistry","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":19},{"question":"A character based on this character learns about grammar from a Verb Fairy in a novel by Audrey Mayhew Allen. This character is mocked for knowing the meaning of the word “beautify” but not being able to figure out what “uglification” means. This character is likely named after a real-life person whose father co-edited the standard Greek-English lexicon with Robert (*) Scott. This character learns that a word means “flimsy and miserable” and that a similar word means “lithe and slimy.” Horseshoe-shaped headbands are sometimes named after this character, who is shown wearing them in John Tenniel’s illustrations. Humpty Dumpty explains the meanings of nonsense words from “Jabberwocky” to, for 10 points, what girl who visits Wonderland in a Lewis Carroll novel?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Alice<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Alice<\/b><\/u> in Wonderland; accept <b><u>Alice<\/b><\/u>’s Adventures in Wonderland]","answer":"<b><u>Alice<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Alice<\/b><\/u> in Wonderland; accept <b><u>Alice<\/b><\/u>’s Adventures in Wonderland]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":1,"questionNumber":20}],"bonuses":[]}
